Guide to the Freedom to Marry Records
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
Freedom to Marry records
1948-2016
2003-2015
MS 2038
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
106.87
535 boxes
20
1 website
Freedom to Marry (2003-2015) was an organization and campaign founded by Evan Wolfson in 2003, with the sole purpose of legalizing marriage for same-sex couples at both the state and federal level. The campaign formulated a three-part strategy to accomplish its goals: win marriage equality in more states, build support for marriage equality, and end federal discrimination. Freedom to Marry's campaign culminated in 2015 when the Supreme Court decided the landmark case, Obergefell v. Hodges, in favor of marriage equality for same-sex couples. The Freedom to Marry records include incorporation documents, meeting minutes, grant applications, promotional material, correspondence, office memos, legal cases, briefs, amici curiae, administrative files, research files, polling files, websites, and audiovisual materials created by, about, and for Freedom to Marry, a bipartisan campaign, to attain marriage equality for same-sex couples in the United States. The organization's records focus almost exclusively on this goal, and the few materials that do not are related to civil rights for the LGBTQ+ (Lesbian, Gay, Bisexual, Trans, Queer, plus) community. Materials are dated from 1948 to 2016 with the bulk falling between 2003 and 2015, the years that the campaign was active. Material dated prior to 2000 is related to the organization either as historical context or research, or pertains specifically to Evan Wolfson's (Freedom to Marry's founder and president) career prior to the establishment of Freedom to Marry.
Freedom to Marry
Wolfson, Evan, 1957-
Biographical / Historical
Freedom to Marry (2003-2015) was an organization and campaign founded by Evan Wolfson in 2003, with the sole purpose of legalizing marriage for same-sex couples at both the state and federal level. The campaign formulated a three-part strategy to accomplish its goals: win marriage equality in more states, build support for marriage equality, and end federal discrimination. Freedom to Marry's campaign culminated in 2015 when the Supreme Court decided the landmark case, Obergefell v. Hodges, in favor of marriage equality for same-sex couples.
The marriage equality movement gained a victory in 1993 when Evan Wolfson and Dan Foley argued for and won marriage equality in Hawaii before the Hawaii Supreme Court in the case Baehr v. Miike. Despite this victory, anti-marriage equality groups convinced Hawaii to pass a constitutional amendment forbidding same-sex marriage. This was the first of many DOMAs (Defense of Marriage Acts) and Super DOMAs, which defined marriage as a union between a man and a woman for the purposes of state and federal law. Recognizing that for marriage equality to become a reality an affirmative and strategic campaign would be needed, the Evelyn & Walter Haas Jr. Fund approached Wolfson in 2000. Together, Wolfson and the Haas Fund created Freedom to Marry as a sustained affirmative campaign designed to work towards the goal of marriage equality in the United States. The campaign designed a strategy to advocate for marriage equality at the state and federal level. The Evelyn & Walter Haas Jr. Fund seeded Freedom to Marry with a $2.5 million grant.
Freedom to Marry incorporated as a nonprofit in 2003, and was overseen by a board and steering committee with Wolfson acting as president. The structure of Freedom to Marry included departments focused on communications, development, research, political operations, and campaign programs. Freedom to Marry used a three-part strategy which included winning marriage equality in more states, building and growing majority support for marriage, and ending federal discrimination. This strategy, known as the Roadmap to Victory, argued that marriage equality did not need to win every state, but simply enough states to encourage the higher branches of the United States government to act. This strategy formed the foundation for their campaign, which included funding partner organizations through regranting programs, mounting legal challenges in the court, lobbying and political fundraising, and community organization. Freedom to Marry also had a marketing strategy to extend their message to the public.
On June 26, 2015, the Supreme Court of the United States legalized same-sex marriage on a federal level by releasing its decision in Obergefell v. Hodges. On July 9, 2015, Freedom to Marry declared that the campaign was over and the organization was dissolved, as they'd achieved their goal of establishing marriage equality in the United States.
Information in this historical note was primarily drawn from the Freedom to Marry website, as well as from the annual reports found in the Program Files series.
Scope and Contents
The Freedom to Marry records include incorporation documents, meeting minutes, grant applications, promotional material, correspondence, office memos, legal cases, briefs, amici curiae, administrative files, research files, polling files, websites, and audiovisual materials created by, about, and for Freedom to Marry, a bipartisan campaign, to attain marriage equality for same-sex couples in the United States. The organization's records focus almost exclusively on this goal, and the few materials that do not are related to civil rights for the LGBTQ+ (Lesbian, Gay, Bisexual, Trans, Queer, plus) community. Materials are dated from 1948 to 2016 with the bulk falling between 2003 and 2015, the years that the campaign was active. Material dated prior to 2000 is related to the organization either as historical context or research, or pertains specifically to Evan Wolfson's (Freedom to Marry's founder and president) career prior to the establishment of Freedom to Marry.
Evan Wolfson's professional papers (Series I) document Wolfson's career prior to the foundation of Freedom to Marry and include material from Wolfson's time at Lambda Legal, including legal briefs relating to his casework. A bulk of these briefs relate to the case Boy Scouts of American and Monmouth Council, Boy Scouts of America v. James Dale. Wolfson's professional papers document his wide breadth of research for his cases and his leadership within the organizations Lambda Legal and Freedom to Marry. Wolfson's professional papers date from between approximately 1990-2009.
Administrative documents (Series II) detail the organization, activities, and history of Freedom to Marry. These, along with the annual reports, job descriptions and job search documents, the papers of Samiya Bashir, the communication director, and the papers of Thalia Zepatos, director of research and messaging, contain information on the day-to-day running of Freedom to Marry from its inception in 2003 to its culmination in 2015. Additionally, the website provides a significant understanding of the history, structure, and mission of Freedom to Marry.
These records also detail the marketing and financial strategies used by Freedom to Marry and their work with partner organizations. Financial records, such as regranting files and annual reports, demonstrate the partnerships between Freedom to Marry and other civil rights and equal marriage organizations, particularly the Human Rights Campaign, GLAD (GLBTQ Legal Advocates & Defenders), GLAAD (once known as Gay & Lesbian Alliance Against Defamation), Lambda Legal, and the ACLU (American Civil Liberties Union). There is also a significant collection of press clippings, research files, and published material tracking the victories and losses of the marriage equality movement across the United States.
Audiovisual materials (Series VII) consist primarily of television publicity that advocates for marriage equality, or programming produced for or about Freedom to Marry promoting the campaign. Recordings of community events and town halls debating marriage equality are also included.
Arrangement
The records are arranged in seven series: I. Evan Wolfson Files, 1948-2009. II. Administrative Records, 2005-2011. III. Development Files, 2003-2012. IV. Program Files, 1973-2016. V. Regrant Files, 2001-2009. VI. Director of Public Engagement and Director of Research and Messaging Files, 2005-2016. VI. Audiovisual Materials, 1986-2013.
Conditions Governing Access
The Freedom to Marry Records have three levels of access: open to researchers, open with permission from the donors, and closed until 2035.
Series I is closed to researchers until 2035.
Series II-VI have specific access details at the series level.
Series VII is comprised of original audiovisual material. Original audiovisual materials, as well as preservation and duplicating masters, may not be played. Researchers must consult use copies, or if none exist must pay for a use copy, which is retained by the repository. Researchers wishing to obtain an additional copy of non-commercially produced items for their personal use should consult the ordering reproductions information on the Manuscripts and Archives web site.
Separated Materials
Commercially produced material, including books, CDs, DVDs, and VHS tapes have been removed from the records.
Biographical / Historical
Evan Wolfson (1957-) is an attorney and gay rights activist who was the founder and president of Freedom to Marry. He received a B.A. in American History from Yale College (1978) and a J.D. from Harvard Law School (1983). He has worked as a district attorney, a civil rights attorney, and as president of Freedom to Marry. He has been a continuous advocate and activist of marriage equality and gay rights in the United States.
While at Harvard, Wolfson wrote his thesis, Same-sex Marriage and Morality: The Human Rights Vision of the Constitution, on marriage equality for same-sex couples. This work became the foundation for his career. After his graduation from Harvard Law School he briefly taught political philosophy at Harvard College before serving as assistant district attorney for Kings County, New York. He also worked as a pro bono cooperating attorney for Lambda Legal between 1984 to 1989.
Wolfson worked at Lambda Legal Defense and Education Fund and was the director of the Fund's Legal Marriage Project throughout the 1990s. During this time he served as co-counsel along with Dan Foley on Hawaii's landmark case for marriage equality, Baehr v. Miike. He became the first Lambda attorney to argue before the United States Supreme Court when he represented James Dale in Boy Scouts of America et. al. v. James Dale, a case which challenged the Boy Scouts for firing Scoutmaster James Dale due to his sexual orientation. In 2000, Wolfson left Lambda Legal to establish Freedom to Marry, where he focused on marriage equality. He served as president of Freedom to Marry from its inception in 2000 until its dissolution in 2015.
Wolfson wrote the book Why Marriage Matters: America, Equality, and Gay People's Right to Marry, published in 2004. He has also written many articles on marriage equality and gay rights. He won numerous awards in honor of his work to ensure marriage equality, including the MassMutual Vow to Protect award and the Barnard Medal of Distinction. He has been named Distinguished Visitor from Practice at Georgetown Law Center, Distinguished Practitioner in Grand Strategy at Yale University, and Senior Counsel at Dentons.
Information found in this biographical note has been drawn from the Freedom to Marry website.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Evan Wolfson, 2016.
LGBTQ resource; Gay rights -- United States; Same-sex marriage; Homosexuality -- Law and legislation -- United States; Law and politics; Gay activists -- United States; Lawyers -- United States -- 21st century; Civil rights -- United States -- 21st century; Freedom to Marry; Wolfson, Evan, 1957-; Bashir, Samiya A.; Zepatos, Thalia, 1955-; Freedom to Marry; Astraea Foundation; Lambda Legal; Gay and Lesbian Advocates and Defenders; Gay & Lesbian Alliance Against Defamation; GLAAD (Organization: 2013- )
- Evan Wolfson Files, 1948-2009; Series I; 20.5; (44 boxes)
  Conditions Governing Access
  Series I, Evan Wolfson Files, is closed until 1 January 2035 per the collection's deed of gift.
  Scope and Contents
  The Evan Wolfson Files series contains the professional papers of Evan Wolfson, the founder of Freedom to Marry, from his time as an attorney to his work with the Freedom to Marry organization. This series contains Wolfson's early marriage organizing files from his work before the foundation of Freedom to Marry, as well as material from his work with Lambda, Freedom to Marry administration documents, press clippings, legal documents from his time as a practicing attorney, and case files for the Boy Scouts et al. v. James Dale United States Supreme Court case. The papers in this series range from 1948 to 2009, but the bulk fall between the years of 1985 and 2005.
  Arrangement
  This series is arranged into six groupings: General, Early marriage organizing files, Freedom to Marry files, Lambda Legal files, Press clippings, and Research files.
  - General, 1984-2009
    - Address books (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Boy Scouts of America and Monmouth Council, Boy Scouts of America v. James Dale
      - Appendix to petition for a writ of certiorari, 1999 (Box 1, Folder 2)
      - Brief of amicus curiae
        - American Bar Association as amicus curiae in support of respondent, 1999 (Box 1, Folder 3)
        - American Association, The National Association of Social Workers, The American Counseling Association, and the American Ortho-psychiatric Association as amici curiae in support of respondent, 1999 (Box 1, Folder 4)
        - America Civil Rights Union in support of petitioners, 1999 (Box 1, Folder 5)
        - APA in support of respondent, 1999 (Box 1, Folder 6)
        - American Jewish Congress in support of respondent, 1999 (Box 1, Folder 7)
        - Bay Area lawyers for individual freedom (BALIF), et al, in support of respondent, 1999 (Box 1, Folder 8)
        - Becket Fund for Religious Liberty in support of petitioners, 1999 (Box 1, Folder 9)
        - California state club and national club association, 1999 (Box 1, Folder 10)
        - Cities of Atlanta, Chicago, Los Angeles, New York, Portland, San Francisco and Tucson in support of respondent, 1999 (Box 1, Folder 11)
        - Claremont Institute Center for Constitutional Jurisprudence in support of petitioners, 1999 (Box 1, Folder 12)
        - Deans of divinity schools and rabbinical institutions in support of respondent, 1999 (Box 1, Folder 13)
        - Family Defense Council and Mary Cummins in support of petitioners, 1999 (Box 1, Folder 14)
        - Family Research Council in support of petitioners, 1999 (Box 1, Folder 15)
        - Gays and Lesbians for Individual Liberty in support of petitioners, 1999 (Box 1, Folder 16)
        - Individual Rights Foundation in support of petitioners, 1999 (Box 1, Folder 17)
        - Institute for Public Affairs of the Union of Orthodox Jewish Congregations of America in support of petitioners, 1999 (Box 1, Folder 18)
        - John J. Hurley and the South Boston Allied War Veterans Council in support of the petitioners, 1999 (Box 1, Folder 19)
        - LGBT groups in support of respondent, 1999 (Box 1, Folder 20)
        - Liberty Legal Institute in support of petitioners, 1999 (Box 1, Folder 21)
        - National Association for the Advancement of Colored People (NAACP) in support of respondent, 1999 (Box 1, Folder 22)
        - National Legal Foundation, 1999 (Box 1, Folder 23)
        - Pacific Legal Foundation in support of reversal, 1999 (Box 1, Folder 24)
        - Religious associations in support of respondent, 1999 (Box 1, Folder 25)
        - Roland Pool and Michael Geller in support of respondent, 1999 (Box 1, Folder 26)
        - School districts in support of respondent, 1999 (Box 1, Folder 27)
        - Several civil and legal groups in support of respondent, 1999 (Box 1, Folder 28)
        - State of New Jersey in support of respondent, 1999 (Box 1, Folder 29)
        - Support of petitioner, 1999 (Box 2, Folder 1)
        - Supporting petitioners, 1999 (Box 2, Folder 2)
        - Supporting in petitioners, 1999 (Box 2, Folder 3)
        - Support of respondents, 1999 (Box 2, Folder 4)
      - Brief in opposition, 1999 (Box 2, Folder 5)
      - Brief for petitioners, 1999 (Box 2, Folder 6-7)
      - Brief for respondent, 1999 (Box 2, Folder 8-9)
      - Brief of the State of New York, et al as amici curiae in support of respondent, 1999 (Box 2, Folder 10)
      - Brief of public advocate of the United States, Lincoln Institute for Research and Education, Commitee to Protect the Family Foundation, Concerned Women for America, and National Criminal Justice Council as amici curiae in support of petitioners, 1999 (Box 2, Folder 11)
      - Brief of Society of American Law Teachers as amicus curiae in support of respondent, 1999 (Box 2, Folder 12)
      - Brief of United States Catholic Conference and New Jersey Catholic Conference as amici curiae, 1999 (Box 2, Folder 13)
      - Brief of various churches as amicus curiae in support of petitioners, 1999 (Box 2, Folder 14)
      - Joint appendix volume III, 1999 (Box 2, Folder 15-16)
      - Petition for a writ of certiorari, 1999 (Box 2, Folder 17)
      - Reply brief for petitioners, 1999 (Box 2, Folder 18-19)
      - Syllabus, 1999 (Box 2, Folder 20)
      - Volume I, 2000 (Box 3, Folder 1)
      - Writ of Certiorari to the Supreme Court of New Jersey, 1999 (Box 3, Folder 2)
    - Civil rights - initiatives Colorado - Evans v. Romer, 1995-1998 (Box 7, Folder 1-2)
    - Concurring opinion by Kennard, J. (Box 3, Folder 3)
    - Criminal context
      - Hate speech (Box 7, Folder 3)
      - Death Penalty, 1999 (Box 7, Folder 4)
      - Child molestation, 1994 (Box 7, Folder 5)
      - Entrapment brochure, 1993 (Box 7, Folder 6)
      - Juries, Batson, etc, 1994 (Box 7, Folder 7)
      - Juries gender discrimination J.E.B. v. Alabama, 1994 (Box 7, Folder 8)
      - Juries - sample voir dire - sexual orientation, 1994 (Box 7, Folder 9)
      - Juries sexual orientation, 1998 (Box 7, Folder 10)
      - Lewdness Missouri Bar - Tramont, Bryan, 1990 (Box 8, Folder 1)
      - Sexual regulation age of consent laws, 1994 (Box 8, Folder 2)
    - Employment, 1994-1995 (Box 8, Folder 3)
    - Employment Dorr v. 1st Kentucky National Bank, 1984 (Box 8, Folder 4)
    - Employment - gays in the medical profession, 1994 (Box 8, Folder 5)
    - Employment Mica England v. Dallas Police Department, 1994 (Box 8, Folder 6)
    - Employment - sexual harassment Governor's commission, 1992 (Box 8, Folder 7)
    - Gays in legal profession clippings, 1993-1996 (Box 8, Folder 8)
    - Guide for counsel in cases to be argued before the Supreme Court of the United States, 1999 October (Box 3, Folder 4)
    - HIV voir dire, 1992 (Box 8, Folder 9)
    - In the Iowa District Court for Polk County case no CV5965 (Box 3, Folder 5)
    - In the Supreme Court of Iowa no 07-1499, 2009 April 3 (Box 3, Folder 6)
    - Juries: jury questionnaire: gay, 1995 (Box 8, Folder 10)
    - Jury selection materials (Box 9, Folder 1)
    - Jury selection material, 1 (Box 44)
    - List of organizations and individuals filing amicus briefs in support of marriage equality (Box 3, Folder 7)
    - Proper role of the state in preventing HIV transmission through sexual activity occurring outside the home (Box 9, Folder 2)
    - Public lewdness, 1990 (Box 9, Folder 3)
    - Rolodex (Box 4–6)
    - The State of New York court of appeals brief of amicus curiae NAACP Legal Defense and Educational Fund, 2006 April 19 (Box 3, Folder 8)
    - Superior court of New Jersey Appellate division docket no. A-2244-03T5, 2005 June 14 (Box 3, Folder 9)
    - Supreme Court no. 2006-340 (P06-2583) Margaret Chambers v. Cassandra Ormiston (Box 3, Folder 10)
    - Supreme Court of New Jersey docket no. 58,389, 2004 (Box 3, Folder 11-13)
    - Sexual harassment task force gay and lesbian roundtable, 1993 May (Box 9, Folder 4)
    - Sexual harassment task force same-sex harassment, 1996 (Box 9, Folder 5)
    - Woodward v. Gallagher trial - notes and decision, 1992 (Box 9, Folder 6)
  - Early marriage organizing files, 1948-2009
    - Aloha, Marriage? Constitutional and choice of law arguments for recognition of same sex marriage paper, 1995 February (Box 9, Folder 7)
    - Arizona - 2003 Standhardt v. Arizona (Box 9, Folder 8)
    - Attorney work product regarding Defense of Marriage Act, 2003 June-August (Box 9, Folder 9)
    - Burns v. Burns (Georgia), 2001 (Box 9, Folder 10)
    - California, 2001 (Box 9, Folder 11)
    - California State - marriage case, 2008 May 15 (Box 9, Folder 12)
    - California 2000 initiative: 1/15/99 No on knight meeting, 1999 January 15 (Box 10, Folder 1)
    - Canada: case: Hendricks/LeBouf, 1998 (Box 10, Folder 2)
    - Cases
      - Baker v. Vermont complaint, 1997 (Box 10, Folder 3)
      - Baker v. Vermont Lambda amicus (Supreme Court) (Box 10, Folder 4)
      - Baker v. Vermont lower court, 1997 (Box 10, Folder 5)
      - Baker v. Vermont opinion (Trial Court), 1997 December 19 (Box 10, Folder 6)
      - Baker v. Vermont our brief (Box 10, Folder 7)
      - Baker v. Vermont parties briefs (Box 10, Folder 8)
      - Baker v. Vermont plaintiffs' briefs (Trial Court), 1997 (Box 10, Folder 9)
      - Baker v. Vermont states brief (Box 10, Folder 10)
      - Baker v. Vermont victory (Box 10, Folder 11)
      - Baker v. Vermont Vermont Supreme Court amici (con) (Box 10, Folder 12, Box 11, Folder 1)
      - Baker v. Vermont Vermont Supreme Court amici (pro) (Box 11, Folder 2)
      - Baker v. Vermont Vermont Supreme Court reply brief (Box 11, Folder 3)
      - Brause v. Alaska correspondence, 1998 (Box 11, Folder 4)
      - Brause v. Alaska notes/contact information (Box 11, Folder 5)
      - Brause v. Alaska press, 1997 (Box 11, Folder 6)
      - Loving v. Virginia, 1966, 1997 (Box 11, Folder 7)
      - Storrs v. Holcomb (Ithaca, NY) correspondence, 1995-2000 (Box 11, Folder 8)
      - Storrs v. Halcomb (Ithaca, NY) notes, 1996-1997 (Box 12, Folder 1)
      - Storrs v. Halcomb (Ithaca, NY) Tony Greene, 1994 (Box 12, Folder 2)
      - Zablockie v. Redhail, 1978 (Box 12, Folder 3)
    - Coalition (Freedom to Marry)
      - New York City 2003 October 27, 2003 October 24-27 (Box 12, Folder 4)
      - New York City, 2004 January 23 (Box 12, Folder 5)
      - D. C., 2004 March 5 (Box 12, Folder 6)
      - D. C., 2004 April 26 (Box 12, Folder 7)
      - New York City 2004 June 14, 2004 May 25-June 14 (Box 12, Folder 8)
      - D. C., 2004 December 6 (Box 12, Folder 9)
      - D. C., 2005 January 24 (Box 12, Folder 10)
      - New York City, 2005 March 7 (Box 12, Folder 11)
      - New York City, 2005 June 6 (Box 12, Folder 12)
      - 2005 September 12 (Box 12, Folder 13)
    - Credit due judgement and credit due laws paper, Iowa Law Review, 1984 (Box 12, Folder 14)
    - Connecticut (Box 12, Folder 15)
    - Dean v. D.C. notes, 1990-1994 (Box 12, Folder 16)
    - Dean v. D.C. press, 1991-1993 (Box 12, Folder 17)
    - Family relationship third year paper (Box 12, Folder 18)
    - Federal recognition issues (my memo, others), 1996 (Box 12, Folder 19)
    - Federation marriage summit of the states evaluations (Box 12, Folder 20)
    - Federation marriage summit of the states evaluations (Box 13, Folder 1)
    - Freedom to Marry Coalition (FMC) - state teleconference, 1996 August (Box 13, Folder 2)
    - Freedom to Marry Coalition steering committee
      - 1995 October 23, 1995 October 5-November 28 (Box 13, Folder 3)
      - 1995 December 4, 1995 October 27-December 11 (Box 13, Folder 4)
      - 1996 January 29, 1995 December 27-1996 February 5 (Box 13, Folder 5)